A Guide to the Papers of the Janney and Related Gilmour and Pollock Families 1695(1755-1944)1981
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Political letters of 1845 continue to solicit John Janney as a congressional candidate. Janney answers Gibson on January 4, 1845, declining the candidacy and giving his reasons. On February 20, 1845, H. A. White and R. W. Payne, Warrenton, wish to solicit Janny's name as a candidate to represent the Whig party in the 9th Congressional District of Virginia while claiming to understand his repugnance to become a candidate but urging him to change his mind; they discuss the Whigs and the Texas Whigs. Letters of March 1st and 3rd from Janney decline the candidacy and explain his reasons. There is a letter dated [ ] 28, 1845, from J[ohn]; H[ill] Carter to William B. Tyler which mentions the Whigs and John Janney.
Political letters of 1846 chiefly concern the question of holding a Convention of Virginia and the Tariff. On February 4, 1846, there is a letter from Asa Rogers, Richmond, reporting that the Convention question is now under discussion in the House of Delegates and that prominent men are giving speeches [in the House] including [Joel?] Leftwich (1759-1846) of Wythe, leader of the western people; mentioning that [Zachary] Taylor is leaning toward the "extreme west"; referring to representation by whole population for districts as opposed to "white basis"; mentioning the state west of the Blue Ridge and discussing the division of the state. On February 11, 1846, Janney answers Rogers, writing that he is unable to determine public sentiment regarding the subject of a convention and that he feels that the public attention may be drawn to foreign rather than domestic relations. He relates that he is in favor of organizing a convention based upon the "mixed basis" and not upon the "white basis" and says that some of Taylor's people favor the "white basis" and are "under the impression that the additional political power is given to the east because of the taxation upon slaves alone, and not on account of taxation upon property in the mass." Janney also mentions that the speech of J[ohn]; S[trother] Pendleton is being generally well received. John S[trother] Pendleton, Washington, writes on February 24, 1846, requesting Janney's notes on the Tariff subject as he is about to examine the subject, and relating that the news from Europe is good through the prospect of peace attributed to the manner in which [James K.] Polk has managed the business. On March 2, 1846, Janney sends his references on the Tariff subject and a copy of the "Fair Proposition" by A. H. H. Stuart, questions the intelligence of striking down the protective policy and the possible reactions from foreign government, and comments on various reports and expresses his views on the Tariff question. There are letters of introduction, ca. June-July 1846 for Janney, explaining his inquiries into public or common schools, especially in regard to the plan of Free schools. Among the 1847 political papers is a letter, December 19, 1847, from John S[trother] Pendleton, Washington, to Harrison Gray Otis (1765-1848) and Thomas H[andasyd] Perkins (1764- 1865), introducing Janney. There are also extracts, [1847], from General [Zachary] Taylor's letters, August to September 1847, concerning his candidacy for the presidency.
Political letters of 1848 discuss the nomination of Zachary Taylor for the presidency and the Whig party. There is a letter of introduction, January 19, 1848, for Janney from Abbott Lawrence (1792- 1855), Boston, to the residents of Lowell. There are resolutions adopted by the Loudoun Whig meeting on February 14, 1848. On March 3, 1848, John Janney writes to John M[inor] Botts (1802-1869), Washington, concerning the nomination of General Zachary Taylor for the presidency. A circular letter of July 14, 1848, Alexandria, urges action to place Virginia among the Whig States of the Union and includes Virginia election returns for 1844 and 1840. A letter, August 7, 1848, from John Janney to John M[inor] Botts, Washington, concerns their positions on the nomination of Taylor. Botts writes on August 23, 1848, concerning his position on the nomination of Taylor and his belief that [Martin] Van Buren will take many more Whigs in the New England states. On December 20, 1848, Janney writes to B. W. Harrison, having examined the resolutions of the General Assembly of Virginia which were adopted on March 8, 1847. He discusses the issue of slavery and its relationship to Mexico and the new territory, mentioning the Missouri Compromise and the Wilmot Proviso, and the ramifications on the border states and southern states if the Union dissolves.
Political letters of 1849 further discuss the issue of slavery and the new territories. There are letters, February 1849, urging Janney to take the nomination for a seat in the State Senate; there is a letter from Janney to "Fellow Citizens" declining to be a candidate. In a letter of February 28, 1849, Robert E. Peyton, Gordonsdale, inquires whether or not Congress has a right to pass a law prohibiting slavery in the territories acquired from Mexico and whether or not Congress has a right to emancipate slaves in the District or forbid slave trade. In his letter of March 4, 1849, Janney comments on Peyton's letter, believing that it would be a misuse of power for Congress to prohibit slavery in California and New Mexico, claiming to oppose the Wilmot Proviso, stating that people authorized by a state constitution have the power to regulate slavery in their territory, believing that Congress has no right to abolish slavery or to forbid slave trade in the District of Columbia, and relating the possible effects on the District of Columbia if Maryland and Virginia ever became non-slaveholding states. On April 17, 1849, John S[trother] Pendleton, Fredericksburg, writes on his progress as a candidate for Congress. Political papers of 1850 relate to the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1850-1851. There are drafts of resolutions, February 22, 1850, by the citizens of Loudoun County. There is a letter, July 26, 1850, from John Janney "To the People of Loudoun County." A document dated October 1850 to February 1851 includes minutes of the proceedings, the plan proposed, and resolutions for the Committee on the Judiciary of the Convention.
Political letters of 1851-1852 discuss the new constitution and representation based different methods. On May 30, 1851, R[ichard]; W[illiam] N. Noland (1821- ), Albemarle County, inquires about and comments on the defeat of the "mixed basis" in the convention. On May 31, 1851, Janney answers Noland, giving his views on representation and the best method of protecting the east, which he believes is with a "suffrage basis," and commenting on [James French] Strother's motion regarding the vote. R[ichard]; C[assius]; L[ee] Moncure (1805-1882), Fredericksburg, writes on June 23, 1851, concerning the establishment of district courts, having an independent judiciary, the mode of electing appellate judges, and improvements needed in the jury trial in relation to the new constitution. On December 5, 1851, Janney writes to his fellow citizens about his nomination for the office of senate and expressing his opinions on certain matters, including the new constitution and representation by "mixed basis" and "white basis." There are letters, April 2 and 4, 1852, from John W. Tyler, Warrenton, concerning his election as judge of his judicial circuit.
Political letters of 1857-1858 relate to the public land question, politics in general, and the University of Virginia. On March 28, 1857, George E[yster] Senseney, editor, Winchester Republican, refers to the public land question and the injustice in regard to the dispositions of the common domain, comments on [Charles James] Faulkner taking both sides of the land question in order to help his election, and requests to offer his name as a candidate for Congress. On April 3, 1857, Janney writes to Senseney, declining to be a candidate and commenting on the Constitutional Convention of Virginia 1850-1851. There is an interesting letter, April 29, 1858, from V[alentine]; W[ood] Southall ( -1861), Charlottesville, concerning the University of Virginia. He comments disfavorably on the University since "the reign of Democratic terror commenced in Va," claims that the entire visitors board and faculty appear to have been selected because of their political opinions, mentions his disdain for Governor [Joseph] Johnson (1785-1877), refers to the political clique of "Calhoun abstractionists, fire eaters, & disunionists," mentions the visit to the University by [ ] Davis and the discourteous reception which apparently led to the loss of a bill proposing an appropriation to the University, comments passionately on the deplorable state of public affairs, state and federal, refers to [James Buchanan (1791-1868)] "chief magistrate who seems but little removed from lunacy," and touches on other political topics. On May 22, 1848, Southall writes about his dissatisfaction with the course of the Richmond Whig and its involvement in the subject of a revival of the African slave trade.
Political letters and papers of 1860-1862 relate to the Union, the Constitution, and the Convention of Virginia. There are drafts concerning the presidential election and the organization of the Union Party in Loudoun County (October 1860). There are resolutions to be laid before a meeting of the citizens of Loudoun County concerning issues relating to the Union and the Constitution, especially the fugitive slave laws and slavery in the new territories (November-December 1860). There is a draft of Loudoun County resolutions concerning the imminent danger to the Constitution of the United States and the Union (1860). There is an 1861 Electoral Ticket for Jefferson Davis as President and Alexander H. Stephens as Vice-President for the Confederacy. On February 23, 1861, [ ] Huey, Philadelphia, writes to Janney, who is presiding over the Virginia Convention, advising that Virginia must stay in the Union at all costs, expressing his belief that a majority of both houses of Congress and the Supreme Court will be in favor of the South, and inquiring as to what can be gained by secession that is not already secured in the Union. There is a copy of the March 20, 1861 Congressional Record "Our First Grave Constitutional Crisis 1861; Speech of Hon. Dale Alford." On April 18, 1861, J[ohn]; J[ordan] Crittendon (1787-1863), Frankfort, Kentucky, writes concerning the Resolution of the Convention of Virginia in appreciation of Crittendon's efforts in the Senate. A lengthy letter, April 18, 1861, from Charles Cocke, Huntley, Nelson County, questions the outcome of the Convention of Virginia. Cocke writes a passionate political outpouring on the effects of "dissolution of the Union," including "the terrors of a civil strife" and "the subversion of the noblest form of Government." He claims that the Convention "laid down the principle that secession for cause, is justifiable"; comments on South Carolina's reasons for seceding; scoffs at the advocates of secession -- J[ames]; M[urray] Mason (1798- 1871), R[obert]; M[ercer]; T[aliaferro] Hunter (1809-1887), [William] "Extra Billy" [Smith] (1797-1887), S[helton]; F[arrar] Leake (1812-1884), and R[oger Atkinson ?] Pryor (1828-1919); comments on several leaders as good men, including John Janney, William [Cabell] Rives, and others; and, comments that if the "rebel states had stood their ground, [Abraham] Lincoln would have been in a minority in both Houses of Congress..." There are two letters, April 28 and May 1, 1861, from W[illiam] C[abell] Rives, "Castle Hill," Cobham, concerning political matters. The former letter from Rives relays the content of two conversations with the vice-president of the Confederate States, [Alexander Hamilton] Stephens; reveals that he is pleased with "the calm & dispassionate tone of his mind, & the frankness & sincerity with which he expressed his views"; and, claims that Stephens is anxious for a peaceable separation. The latter letter concerns Rives' appointment as one of the delegates to the Congress at Montgomery, and encloses a letter to be laid before the Convention as follows: expressing his acknowledgments for the honor of being elected as one of the Delegates of Virginia to the Congress of the Confederate States and regretfully declines acceptance because of his delicate health. Rives writes a heartfelt, patriotic letter in support of the Commonwealth and its decision of secession. A letter of May 3, 1861 from George W[illiam] Summers (1804- 1868), Kanawha Courthouse, concerns the progress of the Convention of Virginia; inquires about the status of Virginia as a Confederate State, and the possibility of a peaceable separation with the South acting only in defense; and, states the conditions in his region. On May 5, 1861, Rives writes in deference to the wishes and opinions expressed by Janney and A. H. H. Stuart that he has decided "to undertake the mission to Montgomery," and refers to Janney's address to General [Robert E.] Lee upon his appointment to the chief command of our military forces. A letter of June 14, 1861, from Rives concerns his acceptance of the duties of the appointment conferred upon him by the Convention. There is an August 1861 document of the property of John Janney impressed for the use of the Confederate states. There is a letter [1861] "To the People of Loudoun" revealing thoughts on Virginia and the Union and the question of secession and the organization of the Convention of Virginia. On June 9, 1862, F[rancis]; H[arrison] Pierpoint (1814-1899), Wheeling, West Virginia, writing as provisional governor, indicates his desire to restore peace and order in Loudoun and the adjoining counties and warns that he intends to protect the Union men and their property, threatening to send away the secessionists at any sign of trouble.
Political letters of 1865-1868 are chiefly between Janney and Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart and concern the possibility of the reunion of Virginia and West Virginia. There is an October 11, 1865 document, "The Voter's Oath," signed by John Janney. On March 9, 1866, Alexander H[ugh]; H[olmes] Stuart (1807-1891), Staunton, writes concerning his election as one of the commissioners to West Virginia, referring to the resolutions directing them to communicate with the government legislature of West Virginia, and indicating that a postponement would be best witih the commissioners meeting in Richmond some two or three weeks from now to confer with each other and with Governor [Francis Harrison] Pierpont. On March 28, 1866, Stuart encloses a copy of a letter dated March 21st from Governor [Arthur Ingram] Boreman (1823-1896), Wheeling, West Virginia, concerning the resolutions adopted by the General Assembly of Virginia on the subjects of a reunion of the states of Virginia and West Virginia, the settlement of the public debt, and a division of the public property of Virginia as existed prior to the separation. There is a letter, June 19, 1866, from J[oshua] Francis Fisher (1807-1873), concerning his pamphlet ["Concessions and Compromises" ?] before the meeting of the South Carolina Convention, which showed his feelings and principles at the beginning of their troubles. On February 26, 1867, Stuart discusses their resignations and the prospect of delaying them until the new legislature meets and provides his impressions on the current political situation. A letter, June 28, 1867, from William Cabell Rives refers to the Trustees of the Peabody Fund appointment of Dr. [Barnas] Sears (1802-1880) as their general agent. On February 24, 1868, John Janney writes to R. T. Daniel concerning a political address, indicating a change to be made on the statement about the Convention of Virginia that ratified the Constitution of the United States, and mentioning [Robert Mercer Taliaferro] Hunter. On December 25, 1868, Alexander Hugh Holmes Stuart writes that reports indicate that something must be done "to save Virginia from ruin," and mentions [John Brown] Baldwin (1820-1873), [John] Echols (1823-1896), and [ ] Sheffey, who request Janney's presence at a meeting in Richmond. A March 20, 1870 letter from Charles B. Ball, Richmond, to George N. Owing concerns his chances for the judgship. There are several undated political items, including a petition "To the Senate of the United States of America," by the citizens and voters of Philadelphia, requesting an alteration to the Constitution concerning representation as related to slave property. There are also notes: "Reasons for voting against re-eligibility in committee," "Subject of Guarantees" on basis and re- eligibility of government, and on amendments to the Constitution, chiefly regarding representation.
There are transcripts of letters, February - April 1861, from John Janney to his wife, Alcinda "Alice" S. (Marmaduke) Janney while he is in attendance at the Convention of Virginia in Richmond. Although the letters are of a personal nature, Janney does relate his opinions and other information-- some confidential--about the Convention and its progress.
Among John Janney's papers are correspondence and financial and legal papers of Solomon Parsons. There are letters, 1810-1813, from Solomon Parsons to his wife, Harriett E. Parsons. On April 11, 1813, Parsons mentions Admiral [John Borlase] Warren (1753-1822) and his fleet being at the mouth of the Potomac River and refers to his insolence in sending his compliments to their fort. On July 19, 1813, Parsons writes that he believes that the British will come up as far as Dumfries or opposite Occoquan for water before making their escape back, that the town is nearly all soldiers, that he does not know what his part will be yet, and that more troops are arriving. There are letters on October 12 and December 21, 1821, to Henry Gunnell concerning the John Coffey estate and its appraisal. On September 10, 1816, Jacob Parsons, Gloucester, writes about the failure of the tanning business, looking for a new livelihood, and commerce and the fisheries being depressed. There is a letter, February 30, 1828, from Gloucester, referring to the attendance of parties and balls, family news, religious matters, and cousin John [Janney]. There is a June 20, 1829 letter from Baldwin Bradford, Warrenton, to Parsons, concerning an enclosed letter dictated and marked by an African-American woman, Nancy Jackson, requesting another African-American woman, Patsy Johnson, to give ten dollars to Solomon Parsons after her death. It notes that Samuel Johnson, husband of Patsy Johnson, is a free black man who lives with Bradford. The enclosure, February 9, 1829, [Nancy Jackson] to "Dear Master" states her intentions. Letters of July 14 and July 18, 1829 between Parsons and Thomas W. Hewitt concern the John Coffey estate and an inquiry into the sale of the slaves and whether or not they brought as much as they were worth. There is a letter, July 25, 1829, from Mord[ecai] Miller, Alexandria, in which he advises one Sibblefield not to give up the rifles to the government. On September 13, 1829, Jacob Parsons, Gloucester, writes to his brother, commenting on their having similar views on religious subjects yet such differing views on political and commercial topics. On September 24, 1829, A[nthony] P. Gover, Alexandria, refers to foreign affairs, mentioning the Russo-Turkish war and the Russians playing havoc with the Turks and to domestic affairs, mentioning "John Eaton, and the chaste and enlightened cabinet" of Andrew Jackson and the changes to be made in the Custom House offices. Letters of September 24 and October 4, 1829, from John R. Pierpoint, Alexandria, concern the books, James Fenimore Cooper's Works and Ivanhoe [by Sir Walter Scott]. Gover also writes on December 17, 1829, about the speculation in wharf property and the establishment of a foundry and a new ferry in Alexandria. There are interesting letters, October - November 1829, from Fanny B. B. Wilson, "Happy Retreat," Occoquan, to her brother, Solomon Parsons, as a widow with several small children attempting to settle the estate of her late husband, Richard Wilson. She discusses options for making a living such as working part of the farm; the Sheriff calling for a fee bill and taxes and taking her horse, which she hired out for money to buy bread, when she could not pay; the tenant on the Lindsay farm not paying rent; and problems with settling the estate and its outstanding debts. She also lists the names of her six children. Letters of January 12 and March 3, 1830, from J. D. Parsons, Charleston, South Carolina, to his brother chiefly concern business and mention brother Samuel losing his office, his own business being in much confusion, the bankruptcy of a former commercial debtor and ensuing financial problems, and mercantile, agricultural and mechanical operations, and the improvement in business by March. On January 17, 1830, Jacob Parsons, Gloucester, writes about a shipment of a keg of mackerel and there being no sale for fish except mackerel; he also "hopes that Congress will do something toward removing the shackles from commerce" and gives his views on how to maintain a healthy commerce. A letter of February 1, 1830 discusses business progress at Occoquan, mentioning John Morgan selling a great many goods, the factory being in full operation, some thirty good looking and well-dressed girls being well broken in to the business, several houses being built, and the village needing a tailor and a shoemaker. He also mentions freight voyages to St. Thomas, Brazil, and St. Domingo and the effect of the Temperance Society around Alexandria. A letter of March 17, 1830, from Thomas Love, Lebanon, [Ohio], gives a description of the geography of Fairfield, Ohio and surrounding land and waterways; and, mentions various newspapers published in Ohio, the Message from the President [Andrew Jackson], and the tuition at Oxford College, Butler County, Ohio. On March 19, 1830, A[nthony] P. Gover, Alexandria, writes concerning the stir at their town election for councilmen in relation to taxation; the canal dispute and building the road causing much corporate debt; news of local business, including the crockery business of a local, and a foundry and spinning machine maker and the establishment of a ferry on the wharfs. A letter of April 11, 1830 mentions family and local news of Alexandria, John R. Pierpoint being their only boarder, Samuel M. Janney moving to Occoquan, and the house being rented to [Samuel] Carusi, the music and dancing master. A letter of May 13, 1830, from Gover reports the progress on the [Alexandria] canal and refers to the magnitude of the undulation and the wonderful locks. There is another letter, June 15, 1830, from Fanny B. B. Wilson, reporting that she has still not received money or property from the estate because of the lack of an administrator and that she is sending the majority of her children to school. The financial and legal papers of Solomon Parsons refer to the John Coffey estate (February 11, 1807 and January 24, 1827); the farm called "Chantilly" in Fairfax County (September 1, 1818); smith shop accounts, 1821-1823; and, accounts between Solomon Parsons and A[nthony] P. Gover.
Papers of Robert Stevenson Janney